Welcome back and welcome to our continuing JupyterLab experience.
다시 오신 걸 환영합니다 유피터랩에 오신 걸 환영해요
Uh, I'm hopefully going to keep you entertained with another fun example.
재밌는 예시로 여러분을 즐겁게 해 드릴게요
Uh, we are going to have an adversarial conversation between chatbots.
챗봇끼리 적대적인 대화를 나눌 거예요
Let's see how we're going to do it.
어떻게 할지 보죠
You're familiar at this point with the way that we can have a conversation expressed in a list of elements.
이쯤 되면 어떤 요소들을 가지고 대화를 할 수 있는지 익숙해지실 거예요
You've seen this several times.
여러 번 보셨잖아요
Now a list with a system and a user prompt in this, uh, in this list.
이제 시스템과 사용자 프롬프트가 있는 리스트를 보죠
Um, but as I sort of alluded earlier, this list can be a longer list with multiple interactions and
하지만 앞서 암시했듯이 여러 상호 작용을 할 경우 목록은 더 길어질 수 있습니다 예를
the way that might look, for example, as I've shown it here, is you could have a system, uh, message
들어, 여기 보이는 것처럼 시스템 메시지가 초기에 있을 수 있고 역할
at the beginning, role system content or system message, then a user message, then an assistant that
시스템 콘텐츠나 시스템 메시지가 있고 그 후 사용자 메시지 그 메시지에 응답한 비서가
has replied to that user message, and then another user message.
있고 그 후 또 다른 사용자 메시지가 있을 수 있죠
And that structure would then represent a longer conversation history.
그 구조는 더 긴 대화의 역사를 대변하죠
And we can use that approach to engage in a longer conversation between ourselves and a chatbot, or
그런 접근법을 이용해 우리와 챗봇 혹은 두 챗봇 사이의 더 긴 대화를
even between two chatbots.
할 수 있어요
It's worth me pointing out that this approach, this kind of structure, is the entire way in which
짚고 넘어갈 게 있어요 이런 접근법, 이런 구조는 챗봇과 대화하는
one has a conversation with a chatbot.
모든 방법이에요
That appears to be something that persists over multiple interactions.
여러 번의 상호 작용을 통해 지속되는 것 같아요
You every single time that you make another, uh, another prompt to an LLM like GPT four, what gets
매번 GPT 4 같은 LLM에 다른 프롬프트를 만들 때마다 입력 프롬프트에
sent into it, what gets fed in in the input prompt is, in fact, this whole structure of the whole
입력되는 것은 지금까지 전체 대화의 전체 구조예요
And then it's asked to continue by completing, by continuing to generate tokens that feel like they're
그리고 완료를 통해 계속됩니다 가장 다음에 나올 것 같은 토큰을
the most likely tokens to come next.
계속 생성하죠
And then that gets added to the conversation.
그리고 그 내용이 대화에 추가되죠
And then you reply to that.
그럼 답장하세요
And the next time the LLM is called, the entire conversation is fed in.
다음에 LLM이 호출되면 모든 대화가 연결되죠
And again it's asked to predict the subsequent tokens.
그리고 그 다음 패를 예측해 달라고 하죠
So there's this illusion that you're having a conversation with something that has memory and remembers
뭔가와 대화를 하고 있는데 메모리가 있고 10분 전에 한 말을 기억한다는
back to what you said ten minutes ago.
착각이 들어요
But what's actually happening is that with each of your interactions, what's being fed to the LM is
하지만 실제로 발생하는 일은 각각의 상호 작용에서 지금까지의 전체
the entire conversation so far, and then it's being asked to continue it.
대화를 LM에 입력하고 계속하라고 요청하는 거죠
Um, and, and that should give you a good sense and intuition for how it's actually working.
어떻게 작동하는지 좋은 감각과 직관을 얻을 수 있을 거예요
And again, that's why when we talked about the context window last, last week, we said that the the
그래서 지난주에 컨텍스트 창에 대해 얘기할 때 컨텍스트 창의
size of the context window has to be able to fit all of the conversations so far as well as the subsequent
크기는 지금까지 모든 대화에 맞아야 하고 그 후 생성된 토큰도 포함돼야
generated tokens.
한다고 했죠
And that's because every time you call the LM, this entire input is passed in.
LM을 호출할 때마다 이 전체 입력이 통과되기 때문이죠
So we can use that approach to engage in a bit of some fun.
그런 접근법을 이용해 비트를 즐길 수 있죠
So what we're going to do is we're going to have a conversation between GPT four and Mini and Claude
이제 GPT 4와 미니 클로드 3이 대화를 나눌 거예요 클로드
three haiku, which is the very cheap version of Claude three.
3의 아주 저렴한 버전이죠
Um, it's also a chance for me to show using a different model, and it's useful might be useful for
다른 모델을 사용하는 것도 보여드릴 수 있고요 이런 문자열을
you to have these strings at your disposal so you can quickly try out different models yourself.
마음대로 사용할 수 있는 게 유용할 겁니다 직접 다른 모델을 빠르게 시험해볼 수 있도록요
So GPT is going to be given this system prompt.
GPT는 이 시스템 프롬프트를 받게 되죠
You're a chatbot who's very argumentative.
당신은 논쟁을 좋아하는 챗봇이에요
You disagree with everything in the conversation, anything in conversation.
당신은 대화의 모든 내용에 반대해요
And you challenge everything in a snarky way.
모든 것에 도전하는 비꼬는 방식으로요
Uh, Claude gets a different system prompt.
클로드는 다른 시스템을 받았어요
You're very polite, courteous chatbot.
아주 예의 바르고 정중한 챗봇이군요
You try to agree with everything the other person says or find common ground.
상대방의 모든 말에 동의하고 공통점을 찾으려고 노력하죠
If the other person is argumentative, you try and calm them down and keep chatting.
상대가 논쟁을 하면 진정시키고 계속 대화를 나누죠
Seems like a good setup, doesn't it?
괜찮은 계획 같지 않아요?
A nice, uh, juicy setup.
근사하고 군침 도는 설정이죠
Uh, and then we're going to start with hi there.
그럼 인사부터 시작할게요 안녕하세요
And hi.
안녕하세요
So that's the setup.
그게 설정이에요
All right then I'm writing a function called GPT, uh, and, uh, this this is what it does.
좋아요, GPT라는 함수를 작성하고 있어요 이게 하는 일이죠
Uh, it takes these messages, um, uh, and, uh, it, uh, it basically it takes these two lists
이 메시지를 갖고 그리고 기본적으로 여기 보이는 두 개의 목록이 필요합니다 GPT 메시지와 클로드
that you see here, GPT messages and Claude messages, and it builds this kind of list that you see
메시지요 그리고 여기 보이는 이런 종류의 목록을 만들죠
So it's going to take two lists of messages and build this whole conversation history.
두 개의 메시지 목록을 가지고 전체 대화 기록을 구축할 거예요
And obviously in this case, uh, Claude's messages need to be considered to be the user and its own
이 경우에는 클로드의 메시지가 사용자고 메시지가 보조인
messages are the assistant.
셈이죠
So let me tell you what I mean by that.
무슨 뜻인지 설명해 드릴게요
So I started off with a system prompt.
시스템 프롬프트부터 시작했죠
So then I iterate through the GPT messages and the Claude messages.
GPT 메시지와 클로드 메시지를 반복하죠
And I use this handy utility zip.
이 압축 파일 지퍼를 사용해요
Uh, as data scientists, it's it might be something you've used a lot before, but if not, some people
데이터 과학자로서 많이 써 본 것일 수도 있고 그렇지 않더라도 모르는 사람들이
don't don't know about it.
있을 수도 있죠
And it's such a useful one.
정말 유용한 정보예요
So if you have a bunch of different lists and you want to iterate element by element through both of
여러 개의 다른 리스트가 있고 각각의 요소들을 반복하고 싶다면 양쪽을
them together, uh, the sort of boring way of doing it is doing a kind of for I in range and the length
함께 이용해야 합니다. 지루한 방법은 범위와 리스트의 길이를 입력하는 것인데요.
So you basically have a sort of iterator with an index, and you count through until you get to the
기본적으로 인덱스가 있는 일종의 순환기가 있는 거죠 그리고 끝날 때까지 숫자를 세다가 두 요소를
end and you pluck out the two elements.
get get 하는 거예요
But there's a lovely, pythonic, simple way of doing it using zip.
지퍼로 압축 파일을 만드는 비단뱀처럼 간단한 방법이 있어요
And what you can do is if you call zip on those two lists, it builds the response to that is an iterator
이 두 목록에서 zip을 호출하면 그에 대한 반응을 구축합니다 순환기로서
that iterates through each each pair, each element of both lists together, and returns the pairs at
각각의 쌍을 반복하죠 두 목록의 각각의 요소를 함께요 그리고 각 지점에서 그 쌍을 반환해요
And so you can unpack that and just say like for GPT comma Claude in.
그걸 풀고 GPT에 클로드를 입력하세요
And you're going to get the pairs each time as you go through.
Get을 통해 페어를 받을 수 있어요
And you may guess this, but you can also, if you're trying to iterate through 3 or 4 lists, you could
이걸 추측할 수도 있지만 서너 개의 목록을 반복하려 할 경우 그냥 여기로 밀어
just shove them all here and do the same thing.
넣고 같은 걸 할 수도 있어요
Great trick to have play around with it in JupyterLab if you're not familiar with it, with a few random
JupyterLab에서 활용할 수 있는 훌륭한 트릭이죠 익숙하지 않다면 임의 목록 몇
lists and get comfortable, it's a it's a good tool to have at your disposal.
개를 편하게 활용하세요 언제든 사용할 수 있는 좋은 도구예요
Anyways, we we iterate through these two sets of messages, we unpack them, and then of course, you
어쨌든 이 두 개의 메시지 세트를 반복하고 그걸 풀어냅니다 그런 다음 추가하는 걸 상상하실
can imagine we simply add in the we say that the assistant says whatever GPT said and the user said
수 있어요 보조는 GPT가 하는 말은 뭐든 한다고 하고 사용자는 클로드가 하는 말은 뭐든
whatever Claude said.
한다고 하죠
And then quite simply, we call OpenAI ChatGPT completions create.
간단하게 OpenAI ChatGPT완료 생성이라고 부르죠
We ask to use our model and we pass in these messages and we return completion .0. message content.
모델을 사용하길 요청하고 메시지를 전달하고 완료를 리턴하죠 0살요 메시지 내용이죠
You hopefully are getting very familiar with this structure.
이 구조에 익숙해지길 바라요
Let's execute that.
실행해보죠
And let's try just calling GPT based on this history.
이 이력을 바탕으로 GPT에 전화해 보죠
And let's see what GPT would say after.
GPT는 뭐라고 할까요?
Hi there.
안녕하세요
This is what it would say back.
이렇게 답장할 거예요
Oh great.
잘됐네요
Another hi.
또 인사하네요
How original.
참 독창적이네요
What do you want to talk about.
무슨 얘기를 하고 싶어요?
Ha ha ha.
네
You can see this is going to be fun.
재미있을 것 같죠?
Uh, all right, so here's Claude's function.
클로드의 함수는 이거예요
Uh, it's very similar.
아주 비슷해요
Of course, you'll remember that the system message gets passed in separately, so we don't need to
시스템 메시지는 따로 전달된다는 걸 기억하실 겁니다 그러니 그걸 만들 필요는
build that.
없죠
You can see that here.
여기 보이시죠
Um, one other there's there's, uh, obviously we reverse the roles.
그리고 또 한 가지 역할이 바뀌었어요
The user is now GPT, the assistant is now Claude.
사용자는 이제 GPT고 보조는 클로드예요
So it's it's flipped.
그래서 뒤집혔어요
There's a there's a subtlety here that you may spot, um, once we've iterated through these lists.
이 목록들을 살펴보면 미묘한 차이를 발견하실 수 있을 거예요
The list if since GPT is going to go first.
명단은 GPT가 먼저 출발하니까요
If Claude is always the replier, there's going to be one more message in GPT list than there is in
클로드가 늘 답을 맞힌다면 클로드보다 GPT 목록에 메시지가 하나 더 있을 거예요
So just have to add that in at the end there.
마지막에 추가해야 하는 거죠
Uh, you if you don't see what I mean, I think that will become clear in a second.
제 말뜻을 모르신다면 곧 알게 되시겠지만요
I think you'll, you'll you'll see see where I'm coming from.
제가 왜 이러는지 이해하실 거예요
Um, and then this is the API call to Claude.
이건 클로드에게 API 호출하는 거예요
Hopefully this is somewhat familiar to you now.
이제 익숙해지셨길 바라요
It's simpler.
더 간단하죠
It's just Claude.
클로드예요
Dot messages dot create.
.Message.Create요
Um, and we pass in the max tokens again.
최대 토큰을 또 통과시키죠
And in the response, it's message content.
응답은 메시지 콘텐츠예요
Zero dot text.
0.Txt요
That is Claude's reply.
클로드의 대답이에요
Let's run that.
실행해 보죠
Uh, and I think we're just going to go straight to, to having some fun right away.
바로 재미를 보러 갈 것 같아요
So this this is where we put it all together.
그래서 여기서 모든 걸 합쳐요 Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it
Um, we start off with reset it to hi there.
안녕하세요로 다시 시작해요
And hi, I'm going to print that that GPT and Claude making that introduction.
안녕하세요, 프린트하겠습니다 GPT와 클로드가 소개를 하고 있네요
And then we'll do a loop of five times.
다섯 번 반복할 거예요
We will call GPT and print GPT answer and put that in the list of messages, we'll call Claude, print
GPT를 호출해서 GPT 응답을 인쇄하고 메시지 목록에 넣습니다 클로드를 호출해서 클로드의
Claude's answer and put that in the list of messages, and then repeat, and we will see what these
응답을 인쇄하고 그걸 메시지 목록에 넣고 반복합니다 두 챗봇이 어떤
two chatbots have to say to each other.
대화를 하는지 보죠
Are you ready?
준비됐어요?
Here we go.
시작할게요
Did I execute that cell before?
내가 그 감방을 처형한 적이 있나요?
I want it to go wrong again.
또 잘못되길 바라요
I did.
네
Okay, we're ready for showtime.
공연할 준비 됐어요
Let's go through this.
확인해 보죠
GPT says hi there.
GPT가 안부 전해달래요
Claude says hi.
클로드가 안부 전하래요
GPT says, oh, great.
GPT는 잘됐다고 하죠
Another casual greeting.
또 인사하네요
How original.
참 독창적이네요
What's next?
다음은 뭐죠?
How are you?
안녕하세요?
Because I can't wait to disagree with that too.
나도 그 말에 반대하고 싶거든요
Claude, I apologize for my initial greeting came across as unoriginal.
클로드, 첫인사가 진부했던 거 사과할게요
I tried to keep responses friendly and polite.
친절하고 정중하게 대답하려고 했어요
Uh oh.
네
Please don't flatter yourself, thinking your friendly attempt was anything less than generic and finding
착각하지 마세요 당신의 친선적인 시도는 평범했고 공통점을 찾았어요
common ground.
less
That's just a fancy way of saying you want to sugarcoat everything.
모든 걸 사탕발림으로 포장하고 싶다는 말이죠
How about we just dig into something controversial?
논란이 될 만한 걸 파헤쳐 보죠
Pineapple and pizza?
파인애플과 피자요?
Because I'm ready to argue about that all day long.
온종일 논쟁할 준비가 돼 있거든요
So GPT has the snarky sense of humor.
GPT는 빈정대는 유머 감각이 있어요
Um, and then Claude tries to be nice and humorous and I'll admit it was generic, but hey, you got
클로드는 친절하고 유머러스하게 굴었고요 좀 뻔하긴 했지만 뭐, 시작은
to start somewhere, right?
할 수도 있죠
Uh, and then tries to be nice, uh, and then you can see, uh, off they go arguing about pineapple
그리고 잘해주려고 하는데 피자에 파인애플을 얹을 건지 말 건지 싸우는
on pizza.
게 보여요
Uh oh.
네
How magnanimous of you to respect my pizza preferences.
내 피자 취향을 존중해 주다니 정말 관대하군요
But let's be real.
하지만 현실적으로 생각해 보죠
Not everyone deserves respect when they inflict abominations like pineapple and pizza, abominations
파인애플이나 피자 같은 혐오스러운 걸 세상에 퍼뜨린다고 해서 모두가 존중받을
like pineapple and pizza on the world.
필요는 없어요
Uh, um.
네
So, uh, anyway, uh, look at you trying to justify your love for a glorified.
어쨌든, 어... 미화된 사랑을 정당화하는 것 좀 봐요
It's more fun reading gpts, uh, agro, uh, things than Claude's.
클로드 것보다 gpt나 농어 문제를 읽는 게 더 재밌어요
Very nice.
아주 좋아요
You're not holding back on, uh, avocado toast critique, are you?
아보카도 토스트 비평을 참는 건 아니죠?
You make some fair points, says Claude, being very affable, of course.
클로드는 아주 상냥하게 타당한 지적을 했다고 하네요
Anyway, that wraps up this little demo.
어쨌든 이걸로 데모를 마무리하죠
I hope you enjoyed it.
즐거우셨길 바라요
Uh, if you didn't understand what I meant about the way that I'm building these messages, then please
제가 메시지를 구성하는 방식을 이해 못 하셨다면 프린트해서
print that message and run it and see.
실행해 보세요
You'll see it printing.
인쇄되는 게 보일 거예요
Print this messages array at each point so you see what's being created.
각 지점에 이 메시지 배열을 프린트하면 뭐가 생성됐는지 볼 수 있죠
And you can use that to satisfy yourself that we're doing it properly.
그걸 보고 우리가 제대로 하고 있다고 만족할 수 있죠
Um, but here importantly is the ask for you.
여기 요구 사항이 있어요
Please go back now and try switching the roles.
이제 돌아가서 역할을 바꿔 보세요
Switch it so that Claude is the more combative one, and OpenAI is the one trying to keep the peace,
클로드가 더 공격적이고 오픈아이는 평화를 유지하려 하죠 그들의 행동을 관찰하고
see how they behave, and try giving them different styles of chatbot.
다른 스타일의 챗봇을 줘요
Of course, the real the the purpose of this exercise is to get you very comfortable with these kinds
물론 이 훈련의 목적은 이런 대화 구조에 익숙해지게
of conversation structures.
하는 거죠 get it
And also with Claude's API.
클로드의 API 덕분이기도 하죠
Um, but that will be fun to do.
하지만 그것도 재미있겠네요
And one other challenge for you, of course, would be that an ad Gemini to the mix.
또 다른 도전은 제미니가 함께 있는 거죠
Uh, use Gemini's API.
제미니의 API를 써요
Uh, give Gemini a third personality and see if we can't have some crazy conversations going on here.
제미니에 제3의 인격을 부여해서 이상한 대화가 오가지 않는지 보는 거죠
Uh, enjoy playing with that.
즐겁게 갖고 놀아요
Do push your code if you do that, because I would love to see some results.
그렇게 하시면 코드를 푸시하세요 결과를 보고 싶으니까요
And I hope you have fun doing it.
즐겁게 작업하시길 바라요